<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  

  <title>Harmony and Counterpoint</title>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    <icon>/mus106/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <link href="/mus106/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/mus106/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
  <updated>2016-02-26T10:23:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>/mus106/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Brian Moseley</name>
    <uri>/mus106/</uri>
    <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>For Friday, Feb. 25</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-friday-feb-25/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-24T14:01:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-friday-feb-25</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;Two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For Friday&lt;/em&gt;: Using the packet of score excerpts I gave you in class, label (with a bracket) every FLP that you can find. Remember that FLPs come in four basic varieties: 
 (a) prolonging tonic, e.g., T1-DP1-D7-T1; 
 (b) prolonging the motion from dominant to tonic, e.g., D5-D4-T3;
 (c) prolonging the motion from tonic to dominant, e.g., T1-D2-D5; 
 (d) prolonging the motion from dominant prep. to dominant, e.g., DP2-DP1-D7
 And that each of those varieties can take on a passing, neighboring, incomplete neighboring, and double neighboring shape.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the end of next week: Complete &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/vqr9cpmesyfs2au/FLP%20Melody%20Harmonization.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;this melody harmonization assignment&lt;/a&gt;. This will count both as the “melody harmonization” objective for this unit &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; as the T-DP-D-T fundamental objective. If you haven’t yet passed that quiz, this is your chance. I strongly recommend attempting this and showing it to me or to a TA to get feedback before turning it in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Wednesday, Feb. 24</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-wednesday-feb-24/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-22T15:39:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-wednesday-feb-24</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;A few things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete the ‘multi-level sketch’ that we began in class. If you’re having trouble knowing what to do, there is lots of information in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/oaxjhuw7zf0eym6/chapter_10_text.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Chapter 10 of &lt;em&gt;TMM&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You can learn a lot just by looking at the sketches in the chapter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harmonize this melody. Once you’ve written a bass line, complete the inner voices in &lt;em&gt;chorale style.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/mus106/images/melody_harm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Melody Harmonization.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Monday, Feb. 22</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-monday-feb-22/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-19T12:06:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-monday-feb-22</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;Next week is going to be a busy week… We have to finish the FLP chapter, and you’ll be starting dictation assessments as well. In addition to getting ready for tutorials, a few things to work on this weekend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete the melody harmonization assignment I gave you in class.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beginning memorizing the FLP chart I passed out in class. I’d like you to know all of the common FLPs—that is, the ones with asterisks on the sheet. We’ll be using this knowledge a lot next week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you haven’t already, please read pp. 3–10 in Chapter 10 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/oaxjhuw7zf0eym6/chapter_10_text.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Smith’s TMM&lt;/a&gt;. This has to do with sketching on &lt;em&gt;multiple levels&lt;/em&gt;, which we’ll start doing next week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy weekend!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Friday, Feb. 19</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-friday-feb-19/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-18T10:31:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-friday-feb-19</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in class, two things for tomorrow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finish the sketch assignment I gave you last week. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/d3lfg28qydg3kx2/AS2-T%2CDP%2CD%2CT.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Here’s a copy if you need one.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete a setting of the melody for string quartet. Here’s the melody:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/mus106/images/IMG_1866.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;String Quartet melody.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Monday, Feb. 15</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-monday-feb-15/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-12T12:10:14-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-monday-feb-15</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;A few things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complete the keyboard style harmonization of the passage we were working on in class. Remember, you are to do a realization for both the antecedent &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the consequent phrases.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work on the analytical sketching assignment that I gave you, which is due by the end of next week. Remember, if you give it to me early, I’ll hand it back with feedback so that you can make corrections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to prepare for your tutorial, especially if you haven’t yet passed the keyboard stuff from this past week.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good weekend!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Friday, Feb. 12</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-friday-feb-10/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-10T12:50:01-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-friday-feb-10</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;I’d like you to do two things for Friday:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Memorize the list of FLPs (functional linear progressions) that we learned in class. You should be able to tell me what kind of dominant chords will fit each of the dominant scale degrees in these patterns. We’ll have a quiz to see if you did this!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Smith’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/oaxjhuw7zf0eym6/chapter_10_text.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Tonal Models of Music, Chapter 10&lt;/a&gt;, read pp. 5–7, on multi-level sketching. Then, study his examples 10.12(a),(b), and (c). You don’t need to read the text surrounding them. Just look over the examples and try to figure them out. We’ll talk through this in class on Friday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the new tutorial information for next week, in the box above.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Wednesday, Feb. 10</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-wednesday-feb-10/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-08T13:40:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-wednesday-feb-10</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;Today’s quizzes are graded and in the envelope outside of my door, and your gradebook has been update. Many of you still need to work on this skill. If you haven’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B0_DrOo8gCUrYUZiSlRIc0Qzenc/preview&quot;&gt;watched my video&lt;/a&gt; from Friday and worked through the exercises in the workbook, &lt;em&gt;do that&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things for Wednesday:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please complete the “Der Wanderer” sketch. I’ll certainly be taking those up to look them over, and on either Wednesday or Friday, I’ll give you a more extended assignment to satisfy the “DP sketch assessment.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read pp. 10-16 of Smith’s Tonal Models of Music, Chapter 10. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/oaxjhuw7zf0eym6/chapter_10_text.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Here’s a link to the Chapter.&lt;/a&gt; As you read, please (1) try to figure out what a “linear progression” is and (2) keep a catalogue of specific linear progressions. This catalogue will be important as we move forward with the next set of assessment objectives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Monday, Feb. 5</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-monday-feb-5/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-05T10:40:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-monday-feb-5</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;We’ll start moving into Chapter 10 next week, which is concerned with “Functional Linear Progressions.” But first, we need to finish up the two objectives associated with Chapter 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you didn’t pass the T-DP-D-T part-writing objective on Friday, you’ll have another chance on Monday. (After that, you need to plan to attempt this during &lt;a href=&quot;/mus106/contact&quot;&gt;office hours&lt;/a&gt;.) See below for help!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each of you needs to be able to complete an analytical sketch involving DP chords. You should finish the sketching assignment we started Friday. We’ll do a bit more practice on Monday, and then I’ll give you an opportunity to pass the objective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you that didn’t pass the assessment Friday (and you can check your gradebook to see), I made a video that walks through how I think about these part-writing exercises. I think it will be helpful and it’s short! Second, you should spend some of this weekend doing the remaining part writing exercises on pp. 137–140. You can find all of the answers to those exercises &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ny4dk43pmlcggxq/DP-D%20Part%20Writing%20Answer%20Key.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. These aren’t the only correct answers, but they all work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B0_DrOo8gCUrYUZiSlRIc0Qzenc/preview&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Friday, February 5</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-friday-february-5/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-04T08:57:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-friday-february-5</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;We will have the first fundamentals quiz tomorrow, where I’ll ask you to write some progression involving dominant preparation chords moving to dominant chords. Use the assignment that was due Monday as practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 9, p. 137, #5: a,b, and c.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 9, p. 138, #6: a,b, and c.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 9, p. 139, #7, a,b, and c.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/igb4f4yotc0tk5n/9%20%28DP%20Harm%29%20WB%20scan.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Here’s a copy&lt;/a&gt; of the Chapter 9 workbook for those of you that don’t have a copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/8z6otd32pclqqvk/9%2C%20Part-Writing%20Answer%20Key.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;here’s an answer key&lt;/a&gt;to check your work against.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Wednesday, Feb. 3</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-wednesday-feb-3/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-02T10:15:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-wednesday-feb-3</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;Sorry about missing class yesterday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow, we’ll have a short practice quiz to see how prepared you are for the first fundamental’s assessment, which will happen on Friday or Monday. On that assessment, you’ll have to write (in chorale or keyboard style) chord progressions that move from various DP chords to D chords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you haven’t already done the workbook assignment that I asked you to complete for Monday, please do that!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’d like you to &lt;em&gt;skim&lt;/em&gt; Chapter 9 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/us3w2m5wihafm66/chapter_9_text.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Text&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/2ae01jissvrh03d/chapter_9_examples.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/a&gt;) for information about ii6, ii6/5, IV6, and ii4/2. Don’t read the whole chapter. Just look for information about these chords. What sorts of generalizations can you make?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I made a short video (below) that you should watch before tomorrow. It’s an introduction to the keyboard tutorial that you’ll have to attempt next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B0_DrOo8gCUrOUVwMDhrTkMyMHM/preview&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Monday, February 1</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/for-monday-february-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-29T10:42:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/for-monday-february-1</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;By the end of next week, we’ll have a fundamentals quiz where you have to “write a complete functional progression containing T-DP-D-T,” in either chorale or keyboard style. This weekend, I want you all to spend some time practicing this skill using some exercises from the workbook. Here’s what you should do. In the workbook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 9, p. 137, #5: a,b, and c. Use ii and at least one ii7.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 9, p. 138, #6: a,b, and c. Use IV and at least one IV7.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 9, p. 139, #7, a,b, and c. Use vi and at least one vi7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About chordal sevenths: remember chordal 7ths “always, always, always” resolve down. In the case of DP chords, you should also try to prepare the 7th in the previous chord, if possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember that when writing ii-V or IV-V, the upper voices should move &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; or remain stationary. And when writing vi-V, upper voices should move &lt;em&gt;up.&lt;/em&gt; There are a few exceptions. Do you remember what they are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/igb4f4yotc0tk5n/9%20%28DP%20Harm%29%20WB%20scan.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;Here’s a copy&lt;/a&gt; of the Chapter 9 workbook for those of you that don’t have a copy. Happy weekend!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome Back!</title>
    <link href="/mus106/blog/welcome-to-mus-105/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-24T07:51:26-05:00</updated>
    <id>/mus106/blog/welcome-to-mus-105</id>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Moseley</name>
      <uri>/mus106/</uri>
      <email>moseleybc@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the second semester of Harmony and Counterpoint! I’m looking forward to working with you all again getting as we learn in more detail how great music works and how we can use that knowledge to shape our own creative activity as musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This term we will working towards the following goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;assimilation&lt;/em&gt; of concepts and techniques common to diatonic music.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;connection&lt;/em&gt; of the concepts to music in myriad styles—including “classical” instrumental and vocal music, and pop/rock music.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the ability to &lt;em&gt;construct&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;deconstruct&lt;/em&gt; phrases and small pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;further developing &lt;em&gt;critical listening skills&lt;/em&gt; through dictation and transcription.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;increased fluency&lt;/em&gt; singing and playing music at the keyboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These goals are about you and your musical and intellectual growth. My goal is to place your work at the center of the class and to learn from you as well. To create an environment where we can try new things and better accomodate the diversity of personalities, I have designed the class so that you have many opportunities to try things without grade penalty. Ultimately, however, its our collective responsibility to make this a great class. I hope that you feel free to come to me with questions and concerns.&lt;/p&gt;


    </content>
  </entry>
  
  
</feed>